Finding Aid for James H. Lincoln Papers 1916-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James H. Lincoln Papers
1916-2001
Lincoln, James H.
Detroit and Harbor Beach, Michigan, resident and Detroit city councilman and later Wayne County juvenile court judge. The collection documents his public career and his interest in family and local history.
85584, Aa/2
8 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by James H. Lincoln (Donor no. 3711 ) in multiple accessions beginning in 1960.
The collection is open for research.
James H. Lincoln was born on August 26, 1916. He was raised on the Lincoln family farm, in Sand Beach Township, south of Harbor Beach, Michigan. James Lincoln began his career in public service in 1938 following his graduation from the University of Michigan working for Frank Murphy. In 1939 he moved to Washington DC to continue working for Murphy who had then been appointed Attorney General of the United States. While living in Washington, Lincoln attended law school classes at Georgetown and also met his future wife, Mary Kimmerling. When Frank Murphy was named justice of the US Supreme Court, Lincoln returned to Michigan and continuing his law school studies. He served for nearly two years in the military during World War II, then following his discharge, he returned to school and received his law degree.
James H. Lincoln opened up his own law office for a time, and became a law partner of future Governor Williams in 1948. In 1951, he worked as executive aide to Senator Blair Moody and headed Moody's Detroit Office. In 1953, Lincoln ran unsuccessfully against incumbent Albert Cobo in the mayoral race for Detroit. In 1954, Lincoln was elected to a vacated seat on Detroit's Common Council. Lincoln was re-elected in 1957 and in 1959. During this time he served both as a councilman and as a member of the Wayne County Board of Supervisors and worked for over five years as the chairman of the Capital Improvement Committee. He played a significant role in the construction of several public buildings as well as the construction of a countywide water system.
During his tenure as city councilman, Lincoln ran for Circuit Court in the spring elections of 1957 and 1959, but was defeated by incumbents in both elections. In May 1960, Governor Williams appointed him probate judge, whereupon he left his position in the City Council. He was later assigned to be a juvenile court judge and served in this position for the rest of his career. When he retired from the bench in 1977, he had served as Wayne County's sole juvenile judge for fifteen years. During his juvenile law career he served on many committees relating to juveniles, including presidency of the National Council of Juvenile Court Justices.
The Lincoln Family has a long history of public service and political association. James Lincoln's grandfather, Lansing Edgar Lincoln, was in the Michigan Legislature. James Lincoln's father, Burr Lincoln, was the Commissioner of Agriculture for the State of Michigan. James Lincoln's brother, Lawrence J. Lincoln was a Lieutenant General in the US Army and had a distinguished military career. Another brother, George A. Lincoln, was a decorated West Point graduate, also serving as Director of the Office of Emergency Preparedness during the Nixon Administration. James Lincoln's mother, Esther Lincoln, worked for many years at the Harbor Beach High School and taught all of her children, as well as Frank Murphy and his siblings. James Lincoln took a great interest in the histories of family members and there lives are documented in his collection as well. His interest in local history continued on in his later life, and he wrote a book about the fires that engulfed the Thumb Region of Michigan in 1881 titled Fiery Trial. He also served as the President of the Frank Murphy Memorial Museum Foundation.
The James H. Lincoln Papers document his role in public service and his active history in local, military and family history. The papers have been organized into four series: Biographical/Personal; Detroit Politics and City Council Activities; Probate Court, Juvenile Court Judge; Genealogy/Historical Research.
Subjects:
Detroit (Mich.); Detroit (Mich.). Common Council.; Detroit (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Forest fires--Michigan--Thumb District.; Harbor Beach (Mich.); Huron County (Mich.); Judges--Michigan--Wayne County.; Juvenile delinquency--Michigan--Wayne County.; Juvenile courts--Michigan--Wayne County.; Lincoln, Burr, 1880-1937.; Lincoln, Esther, 1879-1961.; Lincoln, George A. (George Arthur), 1907-1975; Lincoln, James H.; Lincoln, James H. Fiery trial.; Lincoln, Lansing E. (Lansing Edward), 1842-1916.; Lincoln, Lawrence J. (Lawrence Joseph), 1909-; Lincoln family.; Municipal government--Michigan--Detroit.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; National Council of Juvenile Court Justices.; Water--Fluoridation--Michigan--Detroit.; Water-supply--Michigan--Detroit Region.; Wayne County (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Lincoln, James H.; Courtrooms--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.). Common Council.; James H. Lincoln Hall of Juvenile Justice.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical/Personal
  The Biographical/Personal series includes personal and family correspondence, articles and interviews, speeches, and photographs.
  - Miscellaneous
    - Military service and employment records, 1944-1945 (Box 1)
    - Legal Certification and memberships, 1946-1968 (Box 1)
    - Updated Autobiographical Statement, 1951-1976 (Box 1)
    - Political resume, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Biographical materials, clippings and vita, undated; 1960-1992 (Box 1)
    - Notes on Trip to Iran, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Detroit College of Law Teaching Materials, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Retirement: press releases, invitations, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Resolutions of Tribute and Honor to James H. Lincoln, 1991-1995 (Box 1)
    - Frank Murphy Memorial Museum Foundation, 1994; undated (Box 1)
    - Corrections Commission Resolution of Tribute, 2002 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - Mayor Election Articles, 1953 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings-I, 1953-1954 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings-II, 1953-1954 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1955-1956 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1960-1964 (Box 1)
    - Linda Lincoln Clippings Scrapbook, 1962-1965 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1965-1969 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1970-1975 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1975-1980 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1980-2002 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings, undated (Box 1)
  - Articles and Interviews
    - "This is the Man I Knew" [Lincoln's article on Frank Murphy], 1949 (Box 1)
    - "Thomas Jefferson, Augustus Woodward and a man named George Mason", 1956 (Box 1)
    - "Deciding a Youngster's Fate" in Parke-Davis Review, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Law Journal Articles, 1963-1987 (Box 1)
    - "Lincoln Saga," transcription of interview with Judge Lincoln, 1977-1981 (Box 1)
    - "Last Surviving Pallbearer of Frank Murphy,", undated (Box 1)
    - "University of Michigan interview with Judge Lincoln regarding Frank Murphy" [videocassette], 2002 (Box 1)
  - Speeches
    - Speeches, 1951; undated (Box 1)
    - Speeches, 1955-1956 (Box 1)
    - Speeches, 1957-1959 (Box 1)
    - Speeches, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Speeches, 1992-1999 (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Family, 1941-2002 (Box 2)
    - Portraits, 1954-1977 (Box 2)
    - Group Photographs, 1955-1966 (Box 2)
    - Murphy Memorial and James H. Lincoln Hall of Juvenile Justice, undated (Box 2)
  - Family and Personal Correspondence
    - 1916-1936 (Box 2)
    - 1940-1944 (Box 2)
    - 1945-1949 (Box 2)
    - 1950-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1969 (Box 2)
    - 1970-1979 (Box 2)
    - Retirement Correspondence, 1977 (Box 2)
    - 1980-2001 (Box 2)
- Detroit Politics and City Council Activities
  Detroit Politics and City Council activities documents his campaigns for office and his work in council, most notably concerning issues of regional water supply and the controversy over fluoridation of the city's water in the mid-1950s.
  - Campaigns for Office
    - Mayoralty Campaign, 1953
      - Promotional Materials and Press Releases, 1953 (Box 2)
      - Speech, 1953 (Box 2)
      - Financial Papers, 1953 (Box 2)
    - City Council Campaigns
      - Press Releases and Promotional Materials, 1953-1954 (Box 2)
      - Financial Papers, 1954-1957 (Box 2)
    - Circuit Court Campaign
      - Promotional Materials, Releases, Speeches, 1957 (Box 2)
      - "The Spokesman: Lincoln For Judge" newsletter, 1957 (Box 2)
    - Campaign Correspondence
      - Election correspondence, 1951-1954 (Box 2)
      - Post-Election correspondence, 1954 (Box 2)
      - Election correspondence, 1957 (Box 2)
      - Candidacy correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 2)
  - Organizational Activities
    - Capital Improvement Program Committee, 1955-1960; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Common Council, 1957-1959; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Corporation Council, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
    - Board of Supervisors, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
    - Supervisors Inter-county Committee, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - Council Resolutions introduced by Lincoln, 1955; undated (Box 2)
  - Subject Files
    - Alter-Road Seawall, correspondence, 1958 (Box 2)
    - B -- Miscellaneous, correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
    - Belle Island Bathing Beaches, news articles and statement, 1955 (Box 2)
    - Cobo, correspondence, speech drafts, statements, articles, photographs, 1953-1956 (Box 2)
    - Cub Scouts, correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 2)
    - C -- Miscellaneous, correspondence, reports, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
    - Detroit Port Development, correspondence, clippings, reports, 1958 (Box 2)
    - D -- Miscellaneous, correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
    - Detroit Athletic Club, correspondence, 1958 (Box 2)
    - Detention Home, correspondence, report, 1958 (Box 2)
    - Fiscal Matters of Detroit, memorandum, 1956 (Box 2)
    - Hospitals -- Wayne County General Hospital and Child Hospital, memorandum and correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 2)
    - Jail-Wayne County, correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 2)
    - Jail-Wayne County, correspondence, 1957-1959 (Box 2)
    - Polio Shot Program, resolutions, clippings, notes, 1958 (Box 2)
    - Physically Handicapped Program, resolutions, clippings, 1955-1956 (Box 2)
  - City and Regional Water Issues
    - City-County Water Agreement
      - Report to Board of (Wayne County) Commissioners on an Independent Water Supply, 1955 (Box 3)
      - Proposed County Water System
        - Articles, 1955-1957 (Box 3)
        - Correspondence and map, 1955-1958; undated (Box 3)
      - Water (Capital Improvement Program memoranda and notes), 1956; undated (Box 3)
      - Statements by Lincoln on Water Problem, 1956-1959 (Box 3)
      - Water Project, correspondence, clippings, reports, questionnaires, 1957 (Box 3)
      - City-County Agreement, correspondence, contract proposals, map, 1959 (Box 3)
      - Water Development Program, memoranda and correspondence, 1959 (Box 3)
      - "Information Concerning Proposed Water Agreement" Report by James Lincoln, 1959 (Box 3)
      - Memorandum and Correspondence concerning Development of Water Distribution System in Southwest Michigan, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Fluoridation
      - Correspondence, 1950-1958; 4 folders (Box 3)
      - Statements and Literature
        - "Fluoridation of Water" Statement by Councilman James H. Lincoln, 1956 (Box 3)
        - Fluoridation Articles and Pamphlets, 1956-1959 (Box 3)
        - Conference on Fluoridation Handbook, 1957 (Box 3)
        - Fluoridation, speeches, statements, notes, 1957; undated (Box 3)
- Probate Court, Juvenile Court Judge
  The Probate Court, Juvenile Court Judge series includes correspondence, speeches, and other files pertaining to juvenile crime and related professional involvements.
  - Campaign/Endorsements
    - Selection of Endorsements, correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 3)
    - Campaign Endorsements, correspondence, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence
    - Probate Court correspondence, 1960-1965 (Box 3)
    - Probate Court correspondence, 1965-1970 (Box 3)
    - Probate Court correspondence, 1970-1975 (Box 3)
    - Probate Court correspondence, 1975-1980 (Box 3)
    - Juvenile Traffic Court correspondence, 1960-1975 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence with News Media, 1974-1976 (Box 3)
    - Department of Corrections, Corrections Commission correspondence, 1985 (Box 3)
  - National Council of Juvenile Court Justices
    - Committee on Youth Employment Activities, correspondence and drafts, 1960-1962 (Box 4)
    - Traffic Committee, correspondence and reports, 1960-1965 (Box 4)
    - Central Office Advisory Committee, correspondence, 1968 (Box 4)
    - "A Recommendation on Prison Reform," correspondence, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Central Office Commission, correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
    - American Bar Association, correspondence, 1973-1977 (Box 4)
    - Committee Assignments, 1974-1977 (Box 4)
    - Comments on Proposed Federal Standards on Child Abuse and Neglect, reports, correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
    - Neglected Children's Committee, correspondence, drafts, reports, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Neglected Children's Committee, reports, presentation minutes, correspondence, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Curriculum Advisory Panel, correspondence, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Speeches and Statements
    - Addresses and Speeches of James Lincoln and others upon occasion of the dedication of the Frank Murphy Memorial, 1960 (Box 4)
    - Statements and Speeches, 1960-1967 (Box 4)
    - Statements and Speeches, 1971-1977; undated; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Statement at Dedication of James H. Lincoln Hall of Juvenile Justice, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Subject Files
    - Reports and Memoranda, 1960-1975 (Box 4)
    - Battered Babies and Children, correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 4)
    - Youthful Offenders Act, correspondence, 1965 (Box 4)
    - School Disturbances, correspondence, school leaflets, 1960-1979; 2002 (Box 4)
    - "The Detroit Riot" unedited draft, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - "Anatomy of a Riot" review, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Juvenile Marriage policy, correspondence, 1969-1977 (Box 4)
    - Handwritten notes concerning 1967 Detroit Riots and the legacy of Lincoln's administration, 2002; undated (Box 4)
    - Waste Water Dispute
      - Hercules Inc. Waste Water Dispute, correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 4)
      - Hercules Inc. Waste Water Dispute, clippings, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
- Genealogy/Historical Research
  The Genealogy/Historical Research series consists of binders containing copies of clippings, letters, speeches and other materials concerning his career, the career of Justice Frank Murphy, the development of Detroit's water system in the 1950's, and the genealogy of the Lincoln family of Harbor Beach, Michigan, especially relating to his mother, Esther Lincoln, and the military and governmental careers of his brothers, George A. Lincoln and Lawrence J. Lincoln, his father, Burr B. Lincoln, and his grandfather, Lansing E. Lincoln. This series also consists of collected materials relating to his book Fiery Trial about the great Michigan forest fire of 1881, including letters of reminiscence of survivors and survivors' family members.
  - Family Materials
    - Correspondence, licenses, memorabilia, biographies concerning Lincoln family and Harbor Beach Estate, 15 folders (Box 5)
      (Folders 1-15)
    - Clippings concerning Burr B. Lincoln (Box 5)
      (Folder 16)
    - Wedding Photograph of Burr B. Lincoln (Box 5)
      (Folder 17)
    - "Looking Back" by Carin Carper regarding Philura Lincoln, 1983 (Box 5)
      (Folder 18)
    - "Lincoln Roots" by Lura Lincoln Cook, 1984 (Box 5)
      (Folder 19)
    - George Lincoln, clippings, articles, announcements (Box 5)
      (Folder 20)
    - Clippings concerning Mary Francis Kimmerling (Box 5)
      (Folder 21)
    - Harbor Beach Estate title and land information (Box 5)
      (Folder 22)
    - "An Army Engineer: A Career and A Great Calling" biography of Lawrence J. Lincoln (Box 5)
      (Folder 24)
    - "Book of Esther" written by Lura Lincoln Cook about Esther Hoare, mother of James H. Lincoln (Box 5)
      (Folder 25)
    - Clippings and family biographies, 2 folders (Box 5)
      (Folders 26-27)
    - Notebook I, consisting of genealogical and biographical materials on Lansing Edgar Lincoln, his son Burr Buchanan Lincoln, and his grandchildren George Arthur Lincoln, Lawrence Joseph Lincoln, Philura Harriet Lincoln, and Joyce Bernice Lincoln (Box 6)
    - Notebook II, consisting of genealogical biographical materials of James Helme Lincoln, Mary Francis Kimmerling, his wife, and their children (Box 6)
    - Notebook III, consisting of materials related to Justice Frank Murphy and James H. Lincoln's career as Juvenile Court Judge in Wayne County, Mich., 1960-1977 (Box 6)
    - Notebook IV, consisting of materials related to James H. Lincoln's career as Juvenile Court Judge in Wayne County. (Box 7)
    - Notebook V, consisting of materials related to James H. Lincoln's career as Juvenile Court Judge in Wayne County and his earlier service on the Detroit City Council, including papers concerning Detroit's water system. (Box 7)
  - Fiery Trial Research Files
    - Correspondence Regarding 1881 Fire, circa August-December 1979; August 9, 1979-October 31, 1979; November-December 1979; January 1980-March 1981; 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Frank Murray
      - Frank Murray Receipts, January 1872-September 1881 (Box 8)
      - Frank Murray Insurance Policies, 1877-1880 (Box 8)
      - Frank Murray Correspondence Regarding Losses, Insurance Claims and Relief, September-December 1881 (Box 8)
      - Frank Murray Miscellaneous Records and Correspondence, 1880-1904 (Box 8)
    - Clippings and Subject Files
      - Port Huron Daily Times (September 21 1881) and Huron County News (September 9,10,12,15,17 1881) (Box 8)
      - Newspaper Clippings, August 1946-June 1985 (Box 8)
      - Official Reports, Lighthouse/Navy/War Department, 1881 (Box 8)
      - Michigan Fire Relief Commission Report, 1882 (Box 8)
      - Contemporary Accounts and Reminiscences, September 1881-May 1956 (Box 8)
      - Family Histories (Box 8)
      - Red Cross Correspondence, August 1946-May 1980 (Box 8)
      - Red Cross Articles and Publications, 1881-1981 (Box 8)
      - Judge Lincoln Biographical and Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Manuscripts
      - Fiery Trial Original Manuscript (Box 8)
      - Fiery Trial Manuscripts (Box 8)
      - Fiery Trial Original Boards (Box 8)
      - Photographs, Maps and Related Materials (Box 8)
      - County Histories (Huron, Tuscola) (Box 8)
      - "The Thumb of Michigan" [unfinished manuscript] (Box 8)